So we can now spawn 1 asteroid hazard.
现在我们可以产生1个小行星
But that's far too easy to be a challenge.
不过这样缺乏挑战性
Let's spawn wave after wave of them.
让我们把小行星做成一波波的产生
To get started open the game controller script.
首先打开游戏控制器脚本
The code that we've written works fine
我们编写好的代码
for spawning just one asteroid.
可以正好产生一个小行星
How do we get several of them?
怎么样让它一次多产生一些小行星呢?
Well, we could try to simply duplicate
我们可以单纯的
the code we wrote by copying and
把这段代码复制一下
pasting it several times in our script.
让这段代码在脚本中多执行几次
If we save this script, switch to Unity
保存一下脚本回到Unity
and enter Play mode
进入游戏模式
it kind of works.
似乎还行
We spawn several hazards,
我们一次产生了几个小行星
though if they collide with each other
如果他们产生的时候就碰到了一起
they do blow themselves up.
那么他们就会自行爆炸
But this is less to do with our code
但是这段代码似乎少了点什么
than the fact that we are spawning several
我们需要随机产生
hazards at the same time at random spawn positions.
一些小行星
Is this the correct way to do things?
这段代码是正确的做法么?
Well, frankly, no.
坦白的说,不是
Let's return to our script.
让我们回到我们的脚本
Whenever we write the same code twice
当我们把一段相同的代码写两遍
or more we are almost always doing something wrong.
或者更多次的时候,我们一定是哪里出了问题
This code is terribly ugly.
这段代码太难看了
We need to delete it as soon as possible,
让我们赶快删除这段代码
and good riddance.
这下轻松了
But how do we execute this code multiple
但是我们怎么让这段代码多执行几次
times without simply duplicating it?
但是却不复制这些代码呢?
What we do is we put our block of code
我们将把我们的代码块装进一个
in to a loop and we execute that code
循环体中
each time we cycle through that loop.
每次循环都会执行我们的代码
First let's create a public int called hazardCount.
首先我们新建一个公有的int型变量命名为hazardCount
To hold the number of times we cycle
这个变量保存了
through our loop.
将要循环的次数
We will be able to set this value in the
这个值可以通过Unity中的
Inspector in Unity.
查看器窗口设定
Next let's put our instantiate code in to our loop.
下一步是我们把实例小行星的代码放进循环中
Indent the code we have written
缩进一下我们写好的代码
and write for followed by a set of
然后写下代码for后面跟
parenthesis containing 2 semicolons
左右括号并且括号中写
Surround our code block with brackets
2个分号
We have now put our code in to a for loop.
现在我们的代码被放进了一个for循环
We are not finished yet, but I wanted to
我们还没做完
show you the 2 semicolons here.
但是我想先让大家看看这2个分号
When we are done writing our for loop
当我们把这个for循环写完
it will look very much like a function
它看起来非常像一个
with parameters.
带参数的函数
Parameters in a function are separated by commas.
一般函数的参数是使用逗号分隔的
In a for loop they are statements
在for循环中的条件就好比函数中的参数
and they are separated by semicolons.
他们是被分号分隔的
In the declaration of the for loop
在for循环的声明中
we need to initialise a counter,
我们需要初始化计数器
show the condition, or state how long
注明条件或者
you want to stay in the loop
说明什么停止循环
and then increment our counter.
然后增加我们的计数器
In the initialise step create a new int
在初始化的步骤
variable called i which is set to 0.
我们新建了一个int型的参数i并把它置为0
Our condition will be to stay in the loop
我们的条件设置为
as long as I is less than hazardCount.
I只要比hazardCount就执行循环体
Lastly, every time we cycle through the loop
最后我们每次执行循环的时候都使用
we increment i by 1 using i++.
i++来让i增加1
Now when we execute SpawnWaves
现在如果我们执行SpawnWaves这个函数
we will loop through this code as many
我们将会把生成小行星的代码执行
times as we have set in hazardCount.
hazardCount中设定的值的次数
and then continue on with the function
然后继续执行函数中循环后面剩下的代码
after the loop, which in our case is nothing.
我们这里已经是没有别的代码了
So the function will end.
所以这个函数会结束
Save this script and switch back to Unity to test.
保存代码回到Unity测试一下
Select GameController
选择GameController
and change the hazard count to 10.
把hazard count的值设定为10
Now let's enter and exit Play mode
现在让我们进入退出游戏模式几次
a few times to see what happens.
看看会发生什么
Very much like when we duplicated the code
跟我们复制代码的效果差不多
we are spawning a number of asteroid
我们同时产生了很多
hazards all at once.
小行星
Many are destroying each other on the first
很多都在一开始就因为
frame when they overlap and collide.
产生的位置互相覆盖在了一起而碰撞毁灭了
Better, but not much of an improvement.
代码好了点,但似乎并没好多少
We have simplified our code
我们简化了代码
and we have easy control over the number of
并且让产生小行星的数量
hazards that we spawn.
变得简单容易控制了
But we don't have waves of enemies.
但是这只产生了一波敌人,剩下的几波敌人呢?
What we want our code to do is wait
我们想让代码做到
after spawning each asteroid hazard
产生一个小行星后
before spawning the next.
等一会再产生下一个
So we have a steady barrage of hazards
这样我们可以产生一波小行星灾难的攻势
challenging our player.
挑战我们的玩家
Return to the GameController script.
回到GameController脚本
We need a public float variable called
我们需要一个公有的float(浮点型)参数spawnWait
spawnWait to hold our wait time value.
来保存我们的等待时间
Logically where we want to place our
逻辑上来说
wait code is at the end of the spawn code
等待的代码应该在for循环中
in the for loop before the code loops back
小行星生成的代码之后执行
and spawns the next asteroid hazard.
这样生成下一个小行星前会稍等一会
After instantiate write
在instantiate后面写
wait for seconds spawnWait.
WaitForSeconds(spawnWait)
This is the correct logical place
这是正确的让我们的代码等待
in the code for us to wait
的逻辑顺序
but this syntax does not work in C#.
但是这样并不符合C#的语法
To have a function that can pause
让一个函数暂停
without pausing our entire game
但是并不使整个游戏停止
we need to make this function a coroutine.
我们需要使这个函数成为协程
And coroutines have some very
协程的编写
specific considerations.
有很多具体的注意事项
For more information on coroutines
更多关于协程的信息
please see the lessons and information linked below.
请参考下方连接
For this function to become a coroutine
让一个函数成为协程
we cannot return void.
我们不能让它返回void
We must return IEnumberator.
必须返回IEnumberator
And our WaitForSeconds line
并且我们WaitForSeconds这行代码
must be written as
必须改写成
yield return new WaitForSeconds.
yield return new WaitForSeconds
Lastly we cannot call a coroutine
最后我们并不能像调用函数
like we call a function.
那样调用协程
We must explicitly use StartCoroutine.
我们必须明确使用StartCoroutine调用协程
With either the coroutine's name
并填写协程的名称
or the signature in the parenthesis.
或者插入语的签名
To be polite to our players let's create a new
为了对我们的玩家友善一点
public float variable called startWait.
让我们新建一个startWait的参数
And let's use this as the first line
并把这个参数放到我们
in our new coroutine.
协程的第一行
Copy the spawnWait line
复制spawnWait这行代码
and paste it as the first line of the block.
把他们粘贴到协程内代码的第一行
And change spawnWait to startWait.
把spawnWait 改成startWait
When we set this value in the Inspector
当我们在查看器中设置了这个值的时候
it will be a short pause after the game
游戏开始的时候
starts for the player to get ready,
会有个稍微的停顿让玩家做好准备
get their hands on the controls and
让他们把手放到控制位置
prepare for action.
准备接受挑战
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
With GameController selected
选定GameController
let's set Spawn Wait to 0.5.
设定Spawn Wait的值为0.5
So we will spawn 2 asteroids every second.
所以每秒产生2个小行星
And let's set the Start Wait to 1,
把Start Wait设定为1
giving our players 1 second to get ready.
让我们的玩家有1秒钟的准备时间
Save the scene and enter Play mode to test.
保存场景进入游戏模式测试一下
Now we have a steady stream of hazards.
现在我们有了源源不断的小行星来袭
Let's try that again.
让我们再试一次
Very nice.
完美
But when the first 10 asteroids have
但是当10个小行星
cleared the scene there is nothing
被消灭了以后
more for the player to do.
我们的玩家就没事干了
We could increase our hazard count
我们可以让小行星的数量增加到
to 50, 100, 1000,
50, 100甚至1000
but that could get monotonous,
但是这实在是太单调了
and if our player is good they could
并且如果我们的玩家足够优秀
eventually run out of hazards to shoot or avoid.
这些小行星迟早会被全部躲开或者被击毁
Return to the PlayerController script.
回到PlayerController脚本
We want to create continuous waves of hazards
我们需要源源不断的小行星
until our player is destroyed and the game is over.
直到玩家被消灭或者游戏结束
We can do this by wrapping our instantiate
我们可以通过把实例化的循环
loop in another loop.
嵌套进另一层循环中实现
Grab the for loop code that we have written
and indent that code.
Write while followed by parenthesis.
Wrap the code block in brackets.
This is a while loop.
With a while loop we will continue to
cycle through that loop while the
statement in the parenthesis is true.
Let's say as long as A is greater than B
or whatever statement our code needs.
In this case we will say while true
and of course true will always be true
so this becomes an infinite loop.
We will discuss how to break out of this
infinite loop in another assignment.
The way this works is in our while loop
we execute our for loop
and we instantiate our wave of hazards
based on our hazard count.
When we're done spawning our wave
the while loop brings us back to the top
of the block and we execute the for loop again.
To create a gap between our waves we need
to wait, this time at the end of the while loop.
Write yield return new WaitForSeconds.
Write public float waveWait.
And the amount of time we wait between waves
will be represented by waveWait.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We can see our GameController component
now has a Wave Wait property.
Let's set this to 4.
Save the scene and enter Play mode to test.
There's our first wave of 10 asteroids.
We have a pause between waves as we wait
in our while loop.
and there is another wave as we
execute our for loop again.
Another pause.
And wave 3, and this will continue
until we exit Play mode.
This is starting to look like a real game.
There is one last step we need to do
before we sign off on this segment however.
Look in to our Hierarchy while we're playing the game,
it's full of used explosion clones.
Every time we destroy an asteroid
the asteroid spawns an explosion
and there it stays.
Currently we have only 2 ways of destroying
things in our game.
When they leave the boundary trigger box
and by contact.
Neither will work in this case.
We will need to write another way of
destroying things by time.
Exit Play mode.
Select the Scripts folder
and use the Create menu in the Project view.
Choose C# Script.
Unity creates new assets where we are
focused in the Editor.
By selecting the Scripts folder before we
created our new script Unity created it
inside the Scripts folder,
so there is no need to file it away.
Rename this script DestroyByTime.
And with the script selected open it for editing.
This script will be very simple.
After removing the sample code write
void Start Destroy gameObject.
Now this seems a bit crazy,
destroying our game object the same frame
it's instantiated, no?
Well, Destroy is very useful.
For more information on Destroy see the
lessons and information linked below.
One of the parameters in Destroy is Time.
We can specify a wait time before
Destroy takes effect.
Let's write public float lifetime.
And let's copy lifetime.
After gameObject add a comma
and paste lifetime.
Now when our game object is instantiated
like a ticking time bomb
the object will set it's lifetime and
destroy itself when the time is up.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Select the Explosions folder in Prefabs VFX.
In the Explosions folder are our
explosion prefabs.
Select the Astroid explosion and using the
Add Component button select Scripts
and choose DestroyByTime.
Set the value of lifetime to 2.
We can also add a script this way to multiple items.
Let's update all of our explosion prefabs.
Select the other 2 explosion prefabs
and using multi-object editing
use the Add Component button and select Scripts
and again choose DestroyByTime.
And set the lifetime value to 2 as well.
This adds the script and sets the
lifetime value on both prefabs
at the same time.
Save the scene.
Enter Play mode and test.
We can see the explosion clones are no longer
accumulating in our scene,
not even the player's explosion.
We almost have a complete game!
In the next assignment we will add
audio to our scene.
Including explosion sounds
and laser guns blasting.